Guide to the Roswell Parish Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Roswell Parish papers
1858-1921
MS 1020
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
The papers contain correspondence related to Roswell Parish's attendance at Yale College (Class of 1864), Civil War letters consisting of letters of introduction obtained by Parish in conveying his brother home from the Battle of Antietam and miscellaneous correspondence, autographs, and printed matter. Included in the letters is one from Maxfield Parrish on family genealogy. Among the signatures are those of E. E. Hale, Alvan G. Clark, John T. Morse, N. R. Huntington, Francis A. Walker, Edward H. Hall, Timothy Dwight and E. C. Williams. The Yale letters are chiefly from college officials about Parish's academic standing, but also included are five letters from Walter Camp concerning football.
Parish, Roswell, 1840-1932
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Florence A. Williams, 1959.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Roswell Parish Papers fall into three groups: Yale College materials, Civil War materials, and general materials. The Yale materials consist of letters from College administrators about Parish's academic standing, notices of fraternities, and five letters from Walter Camp concerning football. The Civil War materials are largely letters of introduction which Parish obtained to facilitate conveying his brother, Burleigh, home after he had been wounded in the Battle of Antietam, with some other related materials. Finally, the general materials contain letters and notices about social events, a letter from Maxfield Parrish on Par(r)ish family genealogy, and a selection of autographs cut from letters and documents. Included among the signers are E. E. Hale, Alvan G. Clark, John T. Morse, N. R. Huntington, Francis A. Walker, Edward H. Hall, Timothy Dwight, and E. C. Williams.
Biographical / Historical
Roswell Parish, B.A. 1864.
Born December 3, 1840, in Smithtown, N. Y.
Died August 10, 1932, in Brookline, Mass.
Father, Roswell Parish; engaged in educational work; son of Major Roswell Parish and Lucy (Harris) Parish, of Canterbury, Conn. Mother, Desire (Smith) Parish; daughter of Captain Thomas Smith and Sarah (Smith) Smith, of Smithtown. Yale relatives include: Percy Jackson, '85 S., and Winslow T. Williams, ex-'85 S. (nephews); and E. Winslow Williams, '14 (grandnephew).
Hartford Public High School. Entered Yale with Class of 1863 but left at end of Sophomore year; taught at Hartford Public High School and Columbia Institute for the Deaf in Washington, D. C.,1861-January, 1864; then returned to Yale as a Senior; member Beethoven Society, Brothers in Unity, and Kappa Sigma Epsilon.
Taught mathematics, English and history at Columbia Institute for the Deaf 1864-65 and at Norwich (Conn.) Free Academy 1865-67; agent for New York Life Insurance Company at Worcester, Mass., 1867-68; instructor in mathematics and physics at Worcester High School 1868-1875; conducted a private school under his own name in Worcester 1875-76; instructor in mathematics and physics at Williston Academy 1876-1882 and at Mrs. Quincy A. Shaw's Private School in Boston 1882-87 (principal of academic department 1884-87); conducted a private school for girls under his own name in Boston 1887-1893; instructor in mathematics at Mechanical Arts High School, Boston, from 1893 until retirement in 1911 (acting headmaster in 1894); had since been engaged in compiling genealogical records of his ancestors, John Parish, of Groton, Mass., and Stonington, Conn., and Richard Smith, of Smithtown; member New England Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, Eastern Association of Physics Teachers, and Payson Church (Congregational), Easthampton, Mass.
Married April 30, 1869, in Norwich, Conn., Mary Jeannette, daughter of Marvin and Mary Jeannette (Brinckerhoff) McNulty. One son, Roswell, Jr., ex -'95 S. Mrs. Parish died February 17, 1915.
Death due to carcinoma of the stomach. Buried in Evergreen Cemetery, Boston. Survived by son.
(Taken from Yale Obituary Record, 1931-34, pp. 5-6).
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Autographs; Educators; Camp, Walter, 1840-1932; Clark, Alvan Graham, 1832-1897; Dwight, Timothy, 1828-1916; Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909; Hall, Edward Hagaman, 1858-1936; Huntington, N. R.; Morse, John T., Jr. (John Torrey), 1840-1937; Parish, Roswell, 1840-1932; Parrish, Maxfield, 1870-1966; Walker, Francis Amasa, 1840-1897; Williams, Edward Christopher, 1871-1929; Parrish family; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1864; Yale University -- Sports -- Football
- Inventory
  - Yale College materials
    - Camp, Walter: 5 ALS to Roswell Parish, 1891-1906 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Kappa Sigma Epsilon: notice of initiation ceremony, 1859 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Porter, Noah: notice of admission to Yale, 1859 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Sigma Phi: notice of society meeting, 1858 September 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Thacher, Thomas A.: ALS to Roswell Parish, 1863 December 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Woolsey, T. D.: 2 ALS to Roswell Parish, 1864 July 7, 1869 January 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Civil War materials
    - Buckingham, Gov. William A.: ALS, 1862 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Clark, A. N.: ALS, 1862 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Gallaudet, E. M.: telegram and pass, 1863 November 27, 1864 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Trumbull, Henry Clay: 2 ALS, 1862 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Warner, Dr. A. S.: ALS, 1863 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Welch, H. K. W.: ALS, 1862 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Welles, Edgar: ALS to his father, Gideon Welles, 1862 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General
    - Buckingham, J. M.: printed invitation, [1863?] December 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Gough, John B.: ALS, 1867 September 27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Mosaic Club: notice of meeting, 1865 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Newton, H. A.: ALS, 1863 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Parrish, Maxfield: TLS, 1921 November 8 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Willard, W. H.: ALS, 1867 August 28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Autographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)